A Guide to the Virginia Auditor of Public Accounts - Virginia Penitentiary Records, 1798-1869
Library of Virginia
Library of Virginia
Virginia Auditor of Public Accounts - Virginia Penitentiary Records, 1798-1869
The Library of Virginia
APA 131
4.2 cu. ft. (9 boxes)
Virginia Auditor of Public Accounts
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
Transferred from the Auditor of Public Accounts in 1913.
Biographical Information
On 15 December 1796 the General Assembly approved the purchase of land for the construction of "a gaol and penitentiary house." Thomas Jefferson submitted plans for the institution based on prisons that he had seen in France, but these were not accepted. The General Assembly authorized a design competition and selected Benjamin Henry Latrobe to be the architect. Although inmates first entered the penitentiary in 1800, the structure was not completed until 1804.
In 1823 fire destroyed the interior of the penitentiary. Rebuilding began at once. New buildings were added and a wall was constructed around the perimeter of the facility. In 1833, however, Alexis de Touqueville called the penitentiary "one of the bad prisons of the United States." The physical plant survived the Civil War, although the inmates looted and pillaged it during the Confederate army's evacuation of Richmond on 2-3 April 1865. After the war, new construction began to replace the Latrobe structure, and the last of the old buildings was demolished in 1928.
During the nineteenth and early twentieth centuries, inmates labored under a contract system and produced goods for sale by private firms. The penitentiary employed a series of agents across the state whose duties included selling the goods manufactured at the penitentiary and providing travel money to discharged inmates. Not all of the manufactured goods from the penitentiary were sold; clothing and household items of penitentiary manufacture were donated to the state mental hospitals at Williamsburg and Staunton.
Scope and Content
Records, 1798-1869, including accounts, correspondence, receipts, vouchers, and warrants of the Virginia Penitentiary submitted to the Auditor of Public Accounts. The collection is arranged chronologically in nine boxes, with oversize materials arranged at the end. The bulk of the records relate to the purchase of food and supplies for prisoners, the building and expansion of the Penitentiary, and the sale of articles built by inmates.
The records include accounts of rations furnished prisoners; invoices of materials purchased for the penitentiary; salaries paid to employees; bills for prisoner medical care; correspondence from Virginia governors ordering cash advances for discharged prisoners for travelling expenses; reports and resolutions from the Board of Directors; and lists of materials produced at the Penitentiary and sent to state mental hospitals. Also included are accounts of goods manufactured at the penitentiary and sold by agents throughout the state. The inmates made a variety of products for sale including shoes, nails, twine, horse collars, coats, and spikes, among others.
Of note are records, 1798-1800, detailing the costs of building the Penitentiary, from purchasing bricks, lime, and planks, to payments to contractors and construction workers. Included are accounts of payments to Benjamin Henry Latrobe for his travel expenses and salary for designing the structure. Also included are records detailing additions and repairs to the Penitentiary as well as the purchase of furniture for the facility.
For additional records please see: Records of the Virginia Penitentiary, 1796-1991 (bulk 1906-1970), LVA Accession 41558.
Arrangement
This collection is arranged chronologically.
Contents List
- 1798 January - May (Box 1, Folder 1)
- 1798 June (Box 1, Folder 2)
- 1798 July (Box 1, Folder 3)
- 1798 November - December (Box 1, Folder 4)
- 1799 January - February (Box 1, Folder 5)
- 1799 March (Box 1, Folder 6)
- 1800, 1806 (Box 1, Folder 7)
- 1807 (Box 1, Folder 8)
- 1808 (Box 1, Folder 9)
- 1809 January - August (Box 2, Folder 1)
- 1809 September (Box 2, Folder 2)
- 1809 September - 1810 February [Warrants 309-405] (Box 2, Folder 3)
- 1809 October (Box 2, Folder 4)
- 1809 November (Box 2, Folder 5)
- 1809 December (Box 2, Folder 6)
- 1810 January (Box 2, Folder 7)
- 1810 February (Box 2, Folder 8)
- 1810 March (Box 2, Folder 9)
- 1810 March - July [Warrants 1-60] (Box 2, Folder 10)
- 1810 April (Box 2, Folder 11)
- 1810 May (Box 2, Folder 12)
- 1810 June (Box 2, Folder 13)
- 1810 July (Box 2, Folder 14)
- 1810 August (Box 2, Folder 15)
- 1810 August - December [Warrants 61-145] (Box 3, Folder 1)
- 1810 September (Box 3, Folder 2)
- 1810 October (Box 3, Folder 3)
- 1810 November (Box 3, Folder 4)
- 1810 December (Box 3, Folder 5)
- 1811 January (Box 3, Folder 6)
- 1811 January - March [Warrants 146-172] (Box 3, Folder 7)
- 1811 February (Box 3, Folder 8)
- 1811 March (Box 3, Folder 9)
- 1811 April (Box 3, Folder 10)
- 1811 May (Box 3, Folder 11)
- 1811 June (Box 3, Folder 12)
- 1811 July (Box 3, Folder 13)
- 1811 August (Box 3, Folder 14)
- 1811 September (Box 3, Folder 15)
- 1811 October (Box 3, Folder 16)
- 1811 November - December (Box 3, Folder 17)
- 1812 January - March (Box 3, Folder 18)
- 1812 April - May (Box 3, Folder 19)
- 1812 June - September (Box 3, Folder 20)
- 1812 October - December (Box 3, Folder 21)
- 1813 - 1816 (Box 4, Folder 1)
- 1817 January - July (Box 4, Folder 2)
- 1817 August - December (Box 4, Folder 3)
- 1818 January - May (Box 4, Folder 4)
- 1818 June - September (Box 4, Folder 5)
- 1818 October - December (Box 4, Folder 6)
- 1819 January - February (Box 4, Folder 7)
- 1819 March - April (Box 4, Folder 8)
- 1819 April (Box 4, Folder 9)
- 1819 May - June (Box 5, Folder 1)
- 1819 July - August (Box 5, Folder 2)
- 1819 September - December (Box 5, Folder 3)
- 1820 January - May (Box 5, Folder 4)
- 1820 June - December (Box 5, Folder 5)
- 1821 January - May (Box 5, Folder 6)
- 1821 June - December (Box 5, Folder 7)
- 1822 (Box 5, Folder 8)
- 1831 - 1833 (Box 5, Folder 9)
- 1834 (Box 5, Folder 10)
- 1835 (Box 5, Folder 11)
- 1836 (Box 6, Folder 1)
- 1837 (Box 6, Folder 2)
- 1838 (Box 6, Folder 3)
- 1839 (Box 6, Folder 4)
- 1840-1843 (Box 6, Folder 5)
- 1844-1849 (Box 6, Folder 6)
- 1850-1851 (Box 6, Folder 7)
- 1862 (Box 6, Folder 8)
- 1863 January - March (Box 6, Folder 9)
- 1863 April - June (Box 6, Folder 10)
- 1863 July - September (Box 7, Folder 1)
- 1863 October - December (Box 7, Folder 2)
- 1864 January (Box 7, Folder 3)
- 1864 February (Box 7, Folder 4)
- 1864 February [Warrants] (Box 7, Folder 5)
- 1864 February [Warrants] (Box 7, Folder 6)
- 1864 February [Warrants] (Box 7, Folder 7)
- 1864 March (Box 7, Folder 8)
- 1864 April - December (Box 8, Folder 1)
- 1864 April [Warrants] (Box 8, Folder 2)
- 1864 December [Warrants] (Box 8, Folder 3)
- 1865 January (Box 8, Folder 4)
- 1865 January [Warrants] (Box 8, Folder 5)
- 1865 February - March (Box 8, Folder 6)
- 1865 February [Warrants] (Box 8, Folder 7)
- 1865 April - November, 1869 March (Box 8, Folder 8)
- 1809-1810 [Oversize] (Box 9, Folder 1)
- 1811-1820 [Oversize] (Box 9, Folder 2)
- 1820-1865 [Oversize] (Box 9, Folder 3)